all right let's talk about one of my
favorite topic the tiny human brains
that you can grow in a literal jar if
you want to the ones behind me are
Neanderthal organoids and we will get
there but I want to talk about the
medical applications first if you've
been following me you'd know that I've
been covering these guys for a long time
and yes I will continue to bring you
updates as they come but let's get into
it brain in a jar is no longer a
philosophical question but a reality the
first induced flurry potent stem cells
were invented in 2006 and induced flurry
potent stem cell is the ability to take
a stem cell and then take it back to
something that's more embryonic so that
it can become any cell type there has
been a lot of Fraud and a lot of drama
in this field everyone has been after a
better way to make stem cells that don't
have limitations as a result much of the
research in organoids have started out
with somewhat differentiated stem cells
so skin cells can become neurons and
they're often used but the best way to
make a organoid is to use something
that's already differentiated into that
tissue and this is why fetal brains
embryonic brains are very good as a
starter almost like a bread starter
these guys develop essentially the same
way that a human brain would in
embryonic development except they are
disembodied they can grow eyes and they
are in fact light sensitive so if you
shine light on them they will have some
brain waves so if they had a concept of
a thought it would be there they are
however not considered to be conscious
they are arguably sentient sentients in
this concept is the ability to react to
stimuli with that definition all life is
sentient believe me there has been a
absolute Firestorm of questions about
the ethics of using these guys brain
organoids have actually been around
since 2013 but it wasn't until people
started putting them in robots or using
them for computation that it really hit
the news yes one of my favorite research
Allison M Tre put them in a spider robot
these guys are tiny they're about 10 mm
across at the largest although there's
been a lot of research that's making
them bigger the longer that they develop
the more similar their brain waves
become to that of a fetal human they're
comparable although they are much much
smaller one of the greater limitations
to keeping these guys alive is the
starvation for oxygen because they do
not have a circulatory system there's
been a lot of really cool Research into
how to give them a circulatory system
and some people like Allison has managed
to keep them alive for 10 months longer
they're alive the more complex their
brain waves become the gold standard at
this point for keeping them alive is to
put them in the skull of another animal
and they do integrate they do eventually
have all of the brain waves that you
would expect of a human as long as
they're supplied with blood by another
creature one of the reasons these are so
exciting aside from the spooky as effect
is they have the possibility of healing
brain injuries something we've never
been able to do before there's been
research in trying to heal brain
injuries with just stem cells but it's
never been effective those stem cells do
not end up differentiating into brain
tissue often they can differentiate into
something you don't want I do think part
of that is because once you introduce
new stem cells they then have to
proliferate people who have stem cell
transplants for bone marrow can often
get cancers as a result at no point does
your body want to make a whole ton
of bone marrow but you are inducing A
system that wouldn't normally be there
and if you divide your cells you can end
up with cancer it's not just stress or
radiation that can induce cancer this is
why your body has strict checkpoints
when it comes to yourselves dividing
there is quite a lot of research on
using these guys to heal damaged
portions of the brain and it started in
rodents and more recently has gotten to
monkeys and it is shocking the reason
that they use human brain organoids in
this kind of research is because it
needs to be applicable to human medicine
if you eventually going to move to
humans you don't want all your research
to be in mice and fortunately it takes
hold pretty well when it comes to mice
and rats they're going to use amuno
insufficient variety so they don't have
much of an immune system anyway but your
nervous system is also an a immune
privileged area of the body which means
your immune system is not going to
operate in that area and it's far less
likely to be rejected brain organoids
are essentially fetal human brains they
are baby brains and they can still grow
they still have much more plasticity
than we have in adult brains when you
pop them inside of that skull they can
make projections all the way down to the
brain stem they have no problems with
communicating with mouse neurons at all
in fact you can grow one just simply
near the decapitated spine of a mouse
they did have to teach it that there
were muscles to move with little
electrical impulses and then it kind of
got the hang of it we have had a lot of
success with moving them into animals
who have induced Strokes researchers
damag the area of the brain that
controls for visual relay and the Brain
organoid could go in there and
differentiate into the correct kinds of
tissue it relayed information from the
eyes to the rest of the brain it
restored sight in rodents the reason
that we're not moving directly to humans
is because we want to make sure that we
have the best methods possible before we
start putting them in people because
having that go wrong could hamstring the
entire industry when we work with people
we want it to work this is where some of
the most exciting research has come out
of researchers did put them into the
skulls of monkeys re's monkeys that had
IND do strokes it worked for the most
part but they learned a lot in that
process like they had to wait a little
bit before actually doing the
implantation because otherwise the cells
would not successfully take hold they
also found that you have to use mature
brain organoids they have to establish
themselves a little bit before they go
into that brain I do think we're going
to to see human trials in the very near
future I don't know if they'll go to
chimpanzees first because chimpanzees
can live like 40 years we'll see some
other questions that people often ask
does it have its own Consciousness if
you implant it could it take over I have
no idea maybe join me next time and I'll
tell you about some of the more
disturbing applications like using these
guys as a method of computation and
selling them as a subscription to the
public that is developing by the way
because there's been an international e
to learn how to use them and use them
better and the really cool activity of
creating neanderthals in peace meal
rather than just cloning one which we
probably could do is we just made their
brains